You must be feeling absolutely exhausted at this point.
지금쯤이면 정말 지쳤을 거예요
And if you are, that is okay.
그렇다고 해도 괜찮아요
You have done a phenomenal job.
정말 잘하셨어요
This week has been a grueling week with tons of new information that you've had to take on and from
이번 주는 정말 힘들었죠 새로운 정보가 수없이 많았거든요 처음부터 리더보드와
the beginning, with the leaderboards and the arenas all the way through to our implementation of code
경기장에서부터 코드 번역기 구현까지 프론티어 모델과
translators, both in with frontier models and with open source models.
오픈 소스 모델에서요
We've gone through a lot, and it's been been quite a journey.
많은 일을 겪었고 꽤 긴 여정이었어요
You've acquired a ton of new skills, so I'm here to congratulate you and to tell you that this last
새로운 기술을 많이 익혔으니 축하해주러 온 거예요 그리고 오늘 마지막
session will be quite quick for today as we prepare for the upcoming week.
수업은 꽤 짧을 거예요 다음 주를 준비하니까요
So first of all, just to say, of course, again, it was score one for the frontier.
우선, 다시 말하지만 개척 시대의 음악이었어요
This time we've got to let Claude win the win the show.
이번에는 클로드가 쇼에서 이기게 해줘야 해요
Uh, we had great fun writing software that can write code and translate code between Python and C plus.
파이썬과 C 플러스 간의 코드를 작성하고 번역하는 소프트웨어를 개발하는 건 정말 즐거웠어요
Plus.
더 있어요
And we saw Claude, uh, rule the roost with.
클로드가 대장 노릇을 하는 걸 봤죠
It's a fantastic job of re-implementing those algorithms.
알고리즘을 다시 구현한 건 정말 멋진 일이에요
Um, at the end of today, we're just going to do a little bit more on discussing the performance of
오늘 마무리로 오픈 소스와 비공개 소스 모델의 성능에 대해
open source and closed source models.
좀 더 논의할 텐데요
Um, and we're going to talk about commercial use cases for generating code.
코드 생성 시 상업적 유스 케이스도 다룰 거예요
And there's of course going to be an assignment for you.
물론 당신에게 주어진 과제도 있어요
It's a big assignment for you.
큰 임무잖아요
So whilst this session will be relatively short, the work for you is relatively great and I can't wait
이 세션이 비교적 짧지만 당신에게 주어진 일은 상대적으로 훌륭합니다 어떤 걸 생각해내실지
to see what you come up with.
빨리 보고 싶네요
But first, I want to take a moment to talk about a seriously important problem, a question which is
하지만 먼저 중요하고 중요한 문제에 대해 잠시 얘기하고 싶습니다 여러분의 인공지능
about how do you decide whether or not your AI solution is actually doing a good job?
솔루션이 실제로 잘 작동하는지 어떻게 결정하나요?
Uh, what is what is the what are the techniques for evaluation?
평가할 때 어떤 기술이 필요한가요?
Uh, and it's as I say here, it's perhaps the single most important question, uh, because so much
아까도 말했지만 가장 중요한 질문일 겁니다 성공의 척도는
rides on how you will gauge success.
많은 걸 좌우하니까요
It's something that needs to be thought up front and it needs to be established and worked on.
미리 생각하고 확립하고 연구해야 하는 거죠
Uh, but there are actually two different kinds of performance metrics, and it's important to understand
하지만 성능 지표에는 두 종류가 있습니다 그 차이를 이해하고
the differences between them and to use both in the right context.
적절하게 사용하는 게 중요하죠
The first kind is what sometimes known as model centric or technical metrics.
첫 번째 종류는 모델 중심이라고도 불리는 기술적 측정법이에요
And these are the kinds of metrics that data scientists live and breathe by, because these are metrics
데이터 과학자들은 이런 측정 기준에 목숨을 걸어요 모델을 최적화할
which we can optimize our models with, and they tend to measure in a very immediate way the performance
수 있는 측정 기준이고 모델의 성능을 바로 측정하는 경향이 있거든요
Now I'm going to talk to a couple of these metrics, but not all of them, because some of them are
이제 이런 지표 몇 가지에 대해 말씀드리겠습니다 전부는 아니고요 일부는
more related to traditional machine learning.
전통적인 머신 러닝과 더 관련이 있거든요
And you may already have experience, and it doesn't matter if you don't.
이미 경험이 있을 수도 있고 없어도 괜찮아요
But the first one there, loss is just a general term for talking about how poorly an LLM has performed
첫 번째 항목 손실은 일반적인 용어로 LLM이 작업에서 얼마나 형편없었는지를 뜻합니다
in its task, and is typically used during optimization.
일반적으로 최적화에 사용되죠
You look to try and minimize loss, that is, that is the task of optimization.
손실을 최소화하려고 노력하죠 그게 최적화의 작업이에요
When you are training a model.
모델을 훈련할 때요
The type of loss that we use most frequently in this field is called cross-entropy loss, and this is
이 분야에서 가장 자주 발생하는 손실은 교차 엔트로피 손실이라고 하는데 이렇게 작용해요
So imagine you've got an input set of tokens, a sequence of tokens which is your input text.
여러분의 입력 텍스트인 토큰의 입력 집합과 토큰의 시퀀스가 있다고 상상해 보세요
And you're trying to predict the next token.
다음 토큰을 예측하는 거군요
And you have what the next token actually is in your training data.
훈련 데이터에서 다음 토큰이 무엇인지 알 수 있죠
But as part of training, you're going to try and feed in some amount of this sequence to the model,
하지만 훈련의 일부로 이 시퀀스의 일부를 모델에 피드하려고 할 겁니다 예를 들어
say, predict the next token, and then you're going to have the real next token.
다음 토큰을 예측하고 진짜 다음 토큰을 갖게 되는 거죠
And you want to use something about these two results to calculate a loss.
이 두 결과로 손실을 계산하고 싶겠죠
Here's one way of doing it.
이런 방법도 있어요
What the model actually does is it doesn't just predict the next token in the way I've been saying it
모델이 실제로 하는 일은 다음 토큰을 예측하는 것이 아닙니다 지금까지 제가 말한 방식으로는요
What it really does is gives you a probability distribution of the probabilities of all of the possible
이것은 확률을 분배하는 역할을 합니다. 목록에 있는 다음 토큰의
next tokens that could come in the list.
확률을 말이죠.
And we may, for example, pick the one that has the highest probability.
예를 들어 가능성이 가장 높은 걸 고를 수도 있죠
The way you calculate cross-entropy loss is you say okay, well now we know what the real the true next
교차 엔트로피 손실을 계산하는 방법은 이제 진짜 다음 토큰이 뭔지 안다고
token was.
하는 거죠
Let's find out what probability did the model ascribe to that token?
모델이 토큰에 어떤 확률을 기록했는지 알아보죠
If the actual next thing that was coming was, you know, we started with hello, and the next thing
다음에 나올 것은 hello로 시작해서 다음 것은 단어에
was the token for the word there.
대한 토큰이죠
Then let's look up what kind of probability the model gave to the word there.
그럼 모델이 제시한 단어의 확률을 알아보죠
And that probability is what we will use as the basis for the cross-entropy loss.
그 확률을 교차 엔트로피 손실의 토대로 사용할 거예요
And in fact, to turn it into a loss.
사실, 손실로 바꾸어 놓았죠
Because if we just took the probability that a higher number would be better.
확률을 따져 보면 높은 숫자가 더 낫거든요
And loss is a bad thing, we want to we want a higher number to be worse.
인명 손실은 나쁜 거예요 우리는 인명 손실이 많으면 더 나빠지길 바라죠
So what we do is we actually take the negative log.
그래서 네거티브 로그를 선택해요
We take minus the log of the probability.
확률을 빼고 계산해 보죠
And that might sound a bit confusing.
비트 때문에 좀 헷갈리실 거예요
Why do we do that?
왜 그래야 하죠?
Because if you take the if the probability were one, which would be a perfect answer, it would mean
만약 확률이 1이라면, 그게 완벽한 대답이 되겠죠. 그 말은 다음
that we said there was a 100% likelihood that the next token was exactly the thing that turned out to
토큰이 정확히 다음 토큰이 될 확률이 100%라는 뜻이 되겠죠.
So a probability of one would be a perfect answer.
1의 가능성이 완벽한 답이겠네요
Well, the negative log of one is zero zero loss.
마이너스 1은 0, 0, 0 손실이에요
Perfect answer.
완벽한 대답이에요
So that works.
잘 작동하네요
And if the probability is a very small number, as it gets smaller and smaller, negative log of that
확률이 아주 작은 숫자라면 숫자가 점점 작아질수록 그 숫자에 대한
number as it gets closer and closer to zero becomes a higher and higher positive number.
음수는 0에 가까워질수록 양수가 점점 더 높아져요
So again that works.
이것도 잘 작동하죠
It becomes a loss.
손실이 되죠
A bigger loss is bad news.
손해가 크면 안 좋죠
And so taking the negative log of the probability, the predicted probability of the thing that turned
그래서 확률의 부정적인 로그를 즉, 예상된 확률을 실제 다음 토큰으로
out to be the actual next token, that is called cross-entropy loss and is one of the fundamental metrics
추정한 건데 교차 엔트로피 손실이라고 해요 사용되는 기본 지표 중 하나죠
And very commonly with training LMS, we'll be using it ourselves at some point.
일반적으로 훈련 LMS와 관련해 언젠가 우리가 직접 사용하게 될 텐데요
Uh, another metric that you hear about quite a lot, which is very much related, is called perplexity,
흔히 듣는 또 다른 측정법은 이와 밀접한 관련이 있는데 당혹스러움이라고 해요
which is just, uh, e to the power of cross-entropy loss.
교차 엔트로피 손실의 힘의 약자를 뜻하죠
It means when it turns out to be, is that a perplexity of one would mean that the model is completely
결과가 그렇게 나오면 당혹스럽죠 그 모델은 결과에 대해 완전히 확신하고
confident and correct in its results.
정확해요
It's 100% accurate with 100% certainty.
100% 정확하고 100% 확실하죠
That would give you a perplexity of one.
그럼 한 가지 당혹감이 생기겠죠
A perplexity of two would be like a 50 over 50.
2는 50점 만점에 50점이에요
It's right half the time.
절반은 맞아요
Perplexity of four would be a 25%, uh, probability.
4의 당혹스러움은 25% 확률이에요
So that gives you a sense.
그걸 보면 감이 오죠
A higher, uh, perplexity gives you a sense of of how many tokens would need to be, uh, if all things
더 높고 복잡한 건 토큰이 몇 개 필요한지 알게 돼요 모든 게 평등하다면
were equal, uh, in order to, to predict the next token.
다음 토큰을 예측하기 위해서요
So that gives you a sense of loss and perplexity.
그래서 상실감과 당혹감이 들죠
I won't talk about the others, but you get the sense that these are immediate ways to measure the accuracy
다른 건 언급하지 않겠지만 모델의 정확성 혹은 부정확성을 측정하는
or the inaccuracy of a model that can be used during optimization or for analysis of a model.
즉각적인 방법들이고 모델 최적화나 분석에 사용될 수 있어요.
So that's the model centric metrics.
그게 모델 중심 지표예요
What's the other kind of metrics then?
다른 측정 기준은 뭔가요?
The other kind of metrics are business centric or outcome metrics.
사업 중심 지표나 결과 지표도 있어요
And these these are the ones that are going to resonate the most with your business audience.
이런 것들이 비즈니스 팬들에게 가장 큰 반향을 일으킬 거예요
And ultimately this is the problem that they are asking you to solve.
궁극적으로 그들이 해결하라고 요구하는 문제이기도 하고요
So it's KPIs that are tied to the actual outcomes that your business people have asked for.
따라서 기업 측에서 요구한 실제 결과와 연관된 KPI죠
Maybe it's return on investment.
투자 수익률 같은 거겠죠
Maybe it's if this is meant to be optimizing something, then it's improvements in the time.
최적화를 위한 것이라면 시간이 지나면 개선되겠죠
If you think about what we've just done, then the ultimate metric would be for code.
우리가 방금 한 걸 생각해보면 궁극의 메트릭은 코드에 대한 거예요
For the code solution we just built.
방금 만든 코드 솔루션이요
How much faster is the C plus plus code than the Python code?
C 플러스 플러스 코드가 파이썬 코드보다 얼마나 빠른가요?
How many times faster if it has the same answer?
같은 답을 쓰면 몇 배나 빨라지죠?
So that would be an example of a business centric or outcome metric, because it requires us to to run
비즈니스 중심 혹은 결과 지표의 한 예입니다 전체 제품을 실행하고 결과가
the full product and see what comes out at the end.
어떻게 나오는지 보라는 거니까요
Uh, another example might be that could be comparisons to benchmarks.
벤치마크와 비교할 수 있는 또 다른 예가 있어요
If you're doing something, you're building a, uh, some sort of solution that is then going to surpass
뭔가를 하고 있다면 특정 비즈니스 작업을 수행하는 데 다른
other benchmarks at carrying out a certain business task.
벤치마크를 뛰어넘는 솔루션을 구축하는 거죠
So obviously, the huge benefit of these kinds of metrics is that they are tangible, they are concrete,
따라서 이런 측정법의 큰 이점은 명확하고 구체적인 측정법이 여러분의 사업
and they will speak to your business goals.
목표에 반영된다는 거죠
If you are able to move the needle on these metrics, then you've delivered impact and you can prove
이런 측정값에서 바늘을 움직일 수 있다면 충격을 전달한 것이고 증명할 수 있어요
it.
물론 문제는 모델의 연기와 바로 연결되지 않는다는 거죠
It's related to all sorts of other things, like the kind of data you've got, the environment, how
다른 모든 것과 관련돼 있죠 여러분이 가진 데이터, 환경, 사용 방법 그리고
it's used, and whether the original idea really works in solving the business problem.
원래 아이디어가 정말 비즈니스 문제를 해결하는 데 도움이 되는지 같은 거요
So there's a lot of unknowns that sit between your model's performance and the business metrics.
모델의 성과와 비즈니스 척도 사이에는 미지의 요소가 많아요
But the business metrics have the great advantage of actually being meaningful in the real world.
하지만 비즈니스 지표가 현실에서 의미 있다는 큰 장점이 있어요
So the the answer is you need to use both these kinds of metrics.
그래서 답은 두 가지 측정법을 모두 써야 한다는 거죠
You need to use them in concert.
같이 써야 해요
One allows you to optimize your model to fine tune your model to to demonstrate its its fast performance.
하나는 모델을 최적화해 빠른 성능을 보여주기 위해 미세 조정하는 것이죠
And the other of them is what you use to ultimately prove the business impact behind your solution.
다른 하나는 솔루션 뒤에 숨겨진 비즈니스 영향을 궁극적으로 증명할 때 사용하죠
With that, I'm going to pause in the next session.
다음 세션에선 잠시 중단할게요
We're going to go back one more time and look at our coding solutions, and then talk about what you
한 번 더 돌아가서 코딩 솔루션을 살펴보고 다음 레벨로 넘어가기 위해 무엇을
can do to take it to the next level.
할 수 있는지 얘기해보죠